分开走
We'll split up
王郁和楚良一组
Yu with Chuliang
小兰跟着我
Lan, with me
为什么要拆散我们
Why are we splitting up?
出发前怎么不说
Why didn't you tell us before?
执行命令
Follow orders
如果一组被抓
This way, if one of us gets caught
就不会供出另外一组了
we won't rat out the others
抓紧时间告别吧
Say a quick goodbye
离哈尔滨还有好几百里呢
We're still far from Harbin
对不起
Sorry
我没想到会分开
I didn't think we'd be separated
活着的
Whoever makes it
去找孩子
searches for our children
怎么还能闻见血腥味儿呢
Can you still smell the blood?
想说了
Ready to talk now?
说
Yes
我说
I'll talk
谢先生受惊了
You're scared, Mr Xie
来了几个人
How many came?
你都认识吗
You know them all?
四个
Four
不认识
I don't know them
从哪来
From?
苏联
USSR
来哈尔滨干什么
Why Harbin?
说
They say
说十八号有个秘密行动
there's a secret operation on the 18th
啥秘密行动
What secret operation?
不知道
I don't know
叫
It's called
乌特拉
Utrennya
什么拉
What 'nya?
乌
Ut--
乌特拉
Utrennya
说
They put us
让我们负责配合
in charge of coordination
其他的真不知道
That's all I know
咱也不敢问那
And I didn't dare ask
是去虎头打猎的吗
Are you hunting at Tiger Head?
去苏家屯收皮子的
Collecting hides at Sujia Village
老张
Zhang?
我是老冯
I'm Feng
组织派我来接应你们
We were sent to meet you
咱们坐火车去哈尔滨
We'll take the train to Harbin
沿途敌人设了很多关卡
There will be many traps on the way
搜查很严
They're strict with searches
把枪  指南针
Put guns, compasses,
一切引起敌人怀疑的东西
anything suspicious
都放在这个布袋子里
into this sack
回头有人来取
Someone will collect it
谢谢
Thank you
老冯
Feng
就着烟炮来一口
Got a smoke?
等到了哈尔滨
When you get to Harbin
你帮我整把柯尔特
can you get me a Colt?
左轮
A revolver?
美国人造的
American-made?
不好搞
Hard to find
你找老夏吧
Ask Xia
老夏有路子
Xia has connections
不用找他
We don't need him
我有办法
I have my ways
你是不是还藏了一把枪
You still have a gun on you?
楚良哥说了
Chuliang told me
凡事都得留一手
to always be prepared
枪呢
Where is it?
在身上
On my body
怎么了
What's wrong?
他们是特务
They are spies
别乱看
Don't look
把枪放我手闷子里
Put it in my mitten
给我
Give it to me
不许动
Don't move!
手举起来
Hands up
怎么了
What's wrong?
绑起来
Tie him up
老冯
Feng
误会了吧
You've got it wrong
怎么
What?
小郑
Zheng
还真捆啊你
You're really tying me up
干嘛呢
What are you doing?
轻点
Gently
把手闷子扔过来
Toss me the mitten
再扔
Try again
快点
Hurry
举着手出来
Come out with your hands up
多亏你刚才那一嗓子
It's good you screamed
给了我个机会
It gave me the chance
我故意的
I did it on purpose
你怎么发现他们是特务
How did you know they were spies?
我跟他们提的老夏
Xia, the guy I mentioned
根本没这人
doesn't exist
那他们怎么知道暗号的
How did they know our codes?
有人叛变了
We have a traitor
而且级别不低
high up in the ranks
那得赶紧通知楚良哥和王郁姐啊
We must tell Chuliang and Yu now
这领头的啥来路啊
Tell me about their leader
他叫张宪臣
Zhang Xianchen
早年做记者跑新闻
was a news reporter
四个人里面
Of the four
数他阅历最老
he is the most educated
俩人啊
Two people coming
好像一男一女啊
Seems to be a man and a woman
是不是那个姓张的
Is it Zhang?
我哪知道
How would I know?
我又没看过照片
I've never seen their pictures
发信号
Send the signal
少说话
Keep quiet
不打听
Don't ask questions
他们在苏联受过训
They were trained in the USSR
精得很
They're top-level
一组肯定也联系上了
I'm sure Unit One has made contact
放心
Don't worry
咱们把
Let's put
武器和所有可以暴露身份的东西
everything that can blow our covers
都放在这
and our weapons here
组织会派人来处理
The Organization will handle them
你以后就跟在我身边
From now on, stay close
好好干
Work hard
亏待不了你
You will be rewarded
谢谢
Thank you
科长
Section Chief
发现了老冯他们的尸体
We found Feng and Zheng's bodies
在哪
Where?
五二零三地区
Zone 5203
一组去向不明
Team One's location is unknown
咱们的人正在那带搜索呢
We are searching the area now
老冯不是很有经验吗
Isn't Feng experienced?
咋露馅的
How did he get made?
暗号
The codes
没有问题
are correct
暗号应该没问题
The codes should be correct
二组已经接上头了
Team Two has made contact
一切顺利
All is well
据我所知
From what I know
两组都没带电台
Neither team has radios
你意思是
You mean
一组无法联系二组
Team One cannot contact Team Two?
是
Yes
对
Correct
科长
Section Chief
火车站用不用戒严
shall we tighten security at the train stations?
不
No
放松
Relax them
比以前更松
even looser than before
让他们都上车
Let them all get on the train
用二组引出一组
Use Team Two to draw out Team One
（有叛徒  接头的人是特务）
“Traitors! Contacts are spies”
干啥
Stop
排队会不会啊
Can't you stand in line?
排队
Get in line
听不懂人话啊
Do you speak Chinese?
醉鬼
Drunkard
来  把票都准备好
Get your tickets ready
检票啦
Ticket
票
你的
Yours?
检票呢
I'm just checking tickets
滚远点
Out of the way
证件
Your papers
跟我走一趟
Come with me
为什么
Why?
你是干什么的
Who are you?
特务科的
Special Task Force
我怎么了
Why me?
哪来那么多废话
Cut the crap
例行调查
Standard check
看你就不对劲
You look suspicious
快
Go
刚才特务带走个女孩
That girl just now
是我们的同志
is our comrade
刚才特务带走个女孩
The girl the secret agent just took away
我们得想办法救她
We need to rescue her
一组的
Is she with Team One?
她跟你说什么了
What did she tell you?
没有
Nothing
我们在车里装不认识
We pretended to be strangers
另外一个人呢
And her partner?
没看见
I didn't see him
没在车上
Not on the train?
没有
No
牡丹江站到了
Mudanjiang Station is next
要下车的准备
Prepare to alight
牡丹江站到了
Mudanjiang Station is next
要下车的准备
Prepare to alight
那要先弄清楚
We must determine
那女孩为什么会被带走
why she was taken
下车
Get off
怎么了
What's wrong?
我们坐下一趟车走
We'll take the next train
这趟车不安全
This train is unsafe
那个女同志怎么办
And the comrade?
她可是被特务带走的
She was taken by an agent
这样
Tell you what
你们先走
You go ahead
我想办法
I'll find a way
不行
No.
那样我们都会暴露的
Then we'll all be exposed
走吧
Let's go
换下一趟车
We'll take the next train
腰里有什么东西  给我拿出来
Hand over everything in your belt
听懂我说话了吗
Do you understand?
快点
Hurry
来人啊
Help!
楚良哥王郁姐他们怎么办
What will Chuliang and Yu do?
身边全是特务
They're surrounded by spies
她应该看到密码了
She should have seen the message
他们会有办法
They will find a way
我们还是分开走
We can't stay together
原先的密码写在哪
Where was the coded message written?
这儿
Here
写的什么
What did it say?
说
It said
有叛徒
Traitors!
接头的人是特务
Contacts are spies
你怎么改的
How did you change it?
我就在这改的
I changed it
我改成
to say
一切正常
All normal
十八号哈尔滨见
See you 18th Harbin
所有人不准下车
No one gets off here
我横道河子我得下车
We're going to Hengdaohezi
查完票再下
Have your tickets checked
我横道河子我可以下车吗
We're going to Hengdaohezi
查完再下
Have your tickets checked
把你的票给我
Give me your ticket
在这等着
Wait here
那边人少
Looks quicker over there
排着吧
Stay in line here
过来一下
Come with me
你谁啊
Who are you?
让你过来就过来哪那么多废话
Come when I tell you and shut up
走吧
Let's go
走
Come
你快点
Hurry
证件
Your papers
你
Yours
票
Tickets
横道河子的
You're going to Hengdaohezi?
是啊
Yes
横道河子没事
Hengdaohezi is fine
我们查哈尔滨的
We're checking for those going to Harbin
算了  走
You may go
谢谢啊
Thank you
这边
This way
到前边就跟他们说
Tell them up front
我查过你们了啊
that I've checked you already
谢谢啊  谢谢
Thank you
你们去哈尔滨
You're going to Harbin?
横道河子
Hengdaohezi
带走
Take them away
干嘛
What?
干啥
Why?
你们敢动我  我爸是保长
My father is Head of Security
自己人  误会了
It's a misunderstanding
走吧
Go
都挤什么挤  往后退
Stop crowding! Back up
开门  有人没有
Open up! Anyone there?
开门
Open up!
小兰不会有什么事吧
Lan should be safe, right?
目前我们没有接收到任何情报
We haven't heard otherwise
说明应该没事
So she should be fine
也许他们已经到哈尔滨了
Perhaps they are in Harbin already
老金
Jin
我们去的不是马迭尔的路吧
This isn't the way to The Modern
国联组调查团就住马迭尔
The Investigation Team is staying there
那进出都是密探
It's full of agents
太不安全了
Way too unsafe
那把我们安排在哪啊
Where are you putting us up?
一个旧洋楼
An old mansion
那个开斯普先生堂弟的宅子
belonging to Mr Kasper's cousin
人常年在外国呢
He lives overseas
房子都快荒了
The house is falling apart
我去过
I've been there
一下去那么多人
Wouldn't all of us
不会引起周围人的注意吗
going at once attract attention?
都说那宅子邪性
That house is so spooky
别说人了
people avoid it
鬼也不去啊
Even ghosts won't haunt it
请进
Come on in
小孟
Meng
组织上派来配合工作的
is here to coordinate our work
张姐
Zhang Jie
负责饮食起居
food and accommodations
条件简陋但绝对安全
Spartan, but definitely safe
女同志住后院
Women comrades stay in the back house
这不像前头餐厅
The stove back here
炉子不太旺
Doesn't work as well
不过三个人睡这一张床
But with three of us in one bed
总比一个人暖和
we should be fine
你的腿怎么样
How is your leg?
扭了一下  没事
It's fine, just a sprain
乌特拉行动到底是什么
What is Operation Utrennya?
你知道背荫河吗
You know about Beiyinhe?
日本人的秘密杀人场
The Japanese secret killing grounds?
听说进去的人没有活着出来的
They say no one comes out alive
去年秋天
Last Autumn
那发生了一起越狱事件
there was a prison break there
一个月以后
One month later
日本人就把那个地方炸了
the Japanese bombed it
你说他们是要隐藏什么
What do you think they're hiding there
才付出那么大的代价
to pay such a price to keep it secret?
越狱活下来的人只有一个
Only one escapee survived
叫王子阳
Wang Ziyang
我们的任务就是接他出境
Our mission is to get him over the border
让他在国际社会面前揭露日本人的罪行
to expose the Japanese crime internationally
那现在出了叛徒怎么办
What happens now that we have a traitor?
紧急预案
Emergency protocol
你会用吗
Can you use it?
会
Yes
我专门训练过
I've had training
写吧
Write
下来还需要我们做些什么
What do we do next?
什么都不用做
Nothing
等
We wait
明白
Understood
乌特拉行动
Operation Utrennya
为了这次行动
For this operation
我们整整训练了七个月
we trained seven months
那你们同学啊
You're classmates?
训练时侯认识的
We met in training
算同学吗
Does that make us classmates?
他可是东方大学的高材生
He's a star pupil at Oriental University
我没读过什么书
but I'm not well-educated
没他有文化
Not as cultured as he
那谁训练你们
Who trained you?
苏联教官
Soviet military instructors
都训练什么啊
What were you trained in?
跳伞  射击  格斗
airborne, marksmanship, hand-to-hand
还有俄语
and Russian
你还会俄语呢
You speak Russian?
什么意思啊
What does that mean?
全世界无产者联合起来
Proletarians of the world, unite
什么  什么
What?
不行这太难了
That's too difficult
我刚到苏联的时候
When I first arrived
俄文字母都认不全
I didn't even know the alphabet
直到我啃完了
until I finished reading
《共产党宣言》
The Communist Manifesto
刚才这句话
That quote was taken
就是书里来的
from the Manifesto
来
Come
全世界无产者联合起来
Proletarians of the world, unite
对
Hear, hear
全世界无产者联合起来
Proletarians of the world, unite
来
Come
干杯
Cheers
二十四小时盯着呢
We're on them 24 hours a day
他们现在根本没机会单独交流
They have no chance to communicate
也没办法联系一组
nor contact Team One
你们老出来进去的
Won't they get suspicious
他们不怀疑吗
with you coming and going?
他们很关心一组
They're worried about Team One
让我们轮流出来
and asked us to take turns
打探消息
looking for any sign of them
不会怀疑
I think we're fine
那也尽量减少外出吧
Stay in as much as possible
是
Yes, sir
进来
Enter
科长没事那我先回了
Chief, I'll be off then
赶紧回去吧
Hurry back to the house
书买回来了
I've bought the book
跟那个发报员身上的一模一样
It's identical to the telegram operator's
一个版本
The same edition
这是二组身上带的
This is carried by Team Two
这肯定是乌特拉行动的密码母本
It's definitely the code book for Utrennya
他们就是用这联系的
This is how they communicate
你能破译吗
Can you decipher it?
这真不行
Definitely not
这是苏联人秘密制定的
It was encoded by the Russians
归最高领导人指挥
and used only by the highest leaders
这就是上级给我们的指示
These are our instructions from above
记住它
Remember it
看完了
Have you read it all?
Yes
你能默写下来吗
Can you write it out from memory?
这是我的优势
That is my special skill
所以他们才派我来的
That's why they sent me here
为什么用这么原始的方法传递
What an archaic way to communicate
当组织遭到严重破坏的时候
When the organization is badly damaged
越原始
the most archaic methods
越安全
are the safest
这套密码的母本在楚良哥那
The code book is with Chuliang
怎么翻译
How can we decipher it?
哈尔滨应该能买到这本书
We should be able to find it in Harbin
天亮我去趟书店
I'll go to the book shop in the morning
你别出门
You stay indoors
我等你回来吃饭
I'll have dinner ready for you
给你炖排骨
Braised pork ribs
你长点心
Be more alert
多进出几次
Come and go often
小心敌人堵门
Beware of enemy traps
发现任何不对
If something is wrong
马上走
get out immediately
还有
and
千万别去主动找任何人
don't actively seek out anyone
死等联络信号
Just wait for the communication signal
死记刚才组织给的密码
Memorize the code from the Organization
全凭它才能找到王子阳
That is our only clue to find Wang Ziyang
还没睡
You're still up
睡不着
I can't sleep
不知道楚良哥他们怎么样了
I wonder how Chuliang is doing
你应该当他已经死了
Think of him as though he were dead
为什么这么说
How can you say that?
那王郁姐呢
How about Yu?
你看到前面那片矮房子了吗
Do you see those low houses?
我跟你王郁姐过去就住那
Yu and I used to live there
还有我们的两个孩子
with our two children
五年前刚去苏联没多久
5 years ago, soon after we went to the USSR
收养他们的人就让日本人打死了
their foster parents were killed by the Japanese
最后有人看见他们是在马迭尔宾馆前面要饭
They were last seen begging at Modern Hotel
算起来
By now
姐姐今年应该都八岁了
our daughter should be 8
弟弟也六岁了
and our son should be 6
你知道乌特拉什么意思吗
Do you know what“utrennya”means?
俄语里是黎明的意思
It is the Russian word for "dawn”
对
Yes
黎明
Dawn
天亮了就好了
Everything will be fine when the sun rises
你干嘛
What do you want?
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
我没有名字
I don't have a name
你肚子上是不是有块胎记
Do you have a birthmark on your belly?
你放开我
Let me go
这帮小王八犊子
These little bastards
整天在这儿转悠
swarm around here all day
不干好事
up to no good
找人
Looking for someone?
刚才那孩子
That boy
在这片儿多长时间了
How long has he been here?
有几年了
Years
他是不是还有个姐姐叫小芬
Does he have a sister named Fen?
比他大两岁的样子
She looks about two years older?
这我说不清楚
That I don't know
必须抓活的
We need him alive
谁也不准打死他
No one may kill him
张宪臣  我劝你明智一点
Be smart, Zhang
十八号跟谁见面
Who are you meeting on the 18th?
时间  地点
Time and place?
对这本书你们什么看法
What do you think about this book?
肯定是他们联络的方式
I'm sure that's how they communicate
他原来要去什么地方
Where did he want to go?
行  钥匙给我吧
All right, give me the key
还是没说
He hasn't talked yet?
大小便都失禁了还继续吗
He's incontinent shall we continue?
算了
Forget it
看来是块滚刀肉
He seems tough to break
给他打一针最新进口的迷幻药
Try the latest imported psychedelics
看有用不
See if they work
是
Yes, sir
我来安排
I'll arrange that
有烟吗
Do you have cigarettes?
有
Yes
出去抽根烟
Let's go for a smoke
老周
Zhou
谁叛变了
Who turned on us?
谢子荣
Xie Zirong
王郁他们怎么样
How are Yu and Chuliang?
还好
All right
在周旋
They're preparing
走不了了吧
There's no escape, is there?
你先换上衣服
Change clothes
带上证件
Wear the ID tag
然后拿枪
Take the gun
劫持我
Hold me hostage
冲出去之后
After we charge out
向我开枪
shoot At me
只要打不死我
Anywhere, just
就可以
don't kill me
能走
We can do it
不走了
I wont
我这个身子出去也是废的
I'm worthless trash now
实在完成不了乌特拉行动了
I can't complete Operation Utrennya
不如废物利用
Might as well reuse the trash
咱俩保一个
to keep one of us alive
老周
Zhou
你现在
Right now
比任何人都有活下去的价值
you're worth more alive than anyone else
别固执
Don't argue
你知道我说的是对的
You know I'm right
告诉我
Tell me
告诉我乌特拉行动是什么
What is Operation Utrennya?
接到逃出魔窟的王子阳
Wang has escaped from hell
把他送出境
escort him across the border
但是人在哪儿不知道
But we don't know where he is
去找小兰
Find Lan
她能帮你破解上级的指示
She can decipher your orders
现在应该怎么做
What now?
上那辆白车
Get in the white car
还有吗
Anything else?
王郁他们
Can you help
你能帮着脱身吗
Yu and the others escape?
尽量
I'll try my best
还有吗
Anything else?
还真有件小事
A small favor
马迭尔宾馆前面的小叫花子里头
Among the beggars at Modern Hotel
有我和王郁的孩子
are Yu's and my children
像是我的车啊
That looks like my car
关门
Close the doors
留活口
Take him alive
老张
Zhang
醒醒
Wake up
老张
Zhang
醒醒
Wake up
老张
Zhang
老张啊
你可逃出来了
You made it out!
同志们都盼着你回来呢
The comrades have been waiting for you
谁帮你越的狱
Who helped you escape?
我们要好好感谢他
We must thank him properly
小兰呢
Where is Lan?
你们还要一起执行计划
You must execute the plan together
完成乌特拉行动啊
Complete Operation Utrennya
小兰
Lan
小兰怎么能跟你联络上啊
How will she contact you?
找小兰
Find Lan
亚细亚
As i a
二四六
Tuesdays, Thursdays, Saturdays
头尾
First and last
你觉得他的手铐是怎么打开的
How do you think he opened the handcuffs?
一定有内鬼
It must be an inside job
你这么看
That's what you think?
不然解释不通
There's no other explanation
他用的是金志德的车
He used Jin's car
要不要立即逮捕金志德
Shall we arrest Jin now?
我认为
I believe
他是偶然
he got into that car
才上的那辆车吧
by chance
跟老金没有关系
Jin has nothing to do with this
要真是老金的话
If he did
那他也太笨了
it would be too stupid of him
这样吧
Let's not do anything
先不管他
about that now
你们给我严密监视亚细亚电影院
Keep a tight surveillance on Asia Cinema
是
Yes, sir
周股长来啦
Welcome, Section Head Zhou
我要的药呢
Where is the medicine I wanted?
还没来得及找呢
I haven't had time to find it
还是头疼啊
You still have a headache?
这样
Well
我给您找一盒阿纳辛  您先试试
try this Anacin
周股长
Section Head Zhou
找着盒阿司匹林
I found some Aspirin
谢谢
Thank you
王郁姐病了
Yu is ill
昨晚上吃什么了
What did she eat last night?
不知道啊
I don't know
食物中毒
Food poisoning?
还得住两天
She'll need a few days
这
Here
你吃了
You took it?
你怀疑他们
You suspect them?
他们就是特务
They are spies
你确认吗
Are you sure?
我太了解老张了
The code Zhang wrote on the train
他不会冒着危险写两句废话
must have been changed
火车上的密码
I know him too well
一定被人改过
He wouldn't take an unnecessary risk
有叛徒
There is a traitor
现在我们该怎么办
What shall we do now?
出院的时候动手
When I leave the hospital
我们得跑
We must escape
你看过《伊索寓言》吗
Have you read Aesop's Fables?
我只看过狐狸和鬣狗
I've only read The Fox and the Hyena
你知道狐狸为什么会拒绝它吗
Do you know why the fox refused it?
不知道
I don't know.
为什么不说接头暗号
Why won't you say the contact code?
因为狐狸不知道它是男是女
Because the fox didn't know its gender
我叫周乙
I'm Zhou Yi
是上级党组织
A secret agent operating
安插在特务科的秘密情报人员
from inside the Special Task Force
谢子荣叛变了
Xie Zirong has turned
但他不知道我
But he doesn't know about me
我自己做主
I decided on my own
冒险找到了我的单线联络人
to risk approaching my liaison
想办法弄到了你们的接头暗号
to attain your contact code
为什么要暴露你自己
Why did you expose yourself?
老张被捕了
Zhang has been captured
那小兰呢
And Lan?
小兰暂时安全
She is safe for now
但是老张
But Zhang
被注射了大量的迷幻剂
has been injected with psychedelics
昏迷中
While unconscious
他可能露出了一些
he may have revealed
跟小兰的联络方法
ways to find Lan
叛徒
Traitor
他不是叛徒
He was not
我在现场
I was there
听着
Listen
乌特拉行动
Operation Utrennya
会有别的同志来完成
will be completed by other comrades
你们继续拖住敌人
Keep delaying the enemy
不要轻举妄动
Don't make any rash moves
听从我的安排
Listen to my arrangements
我会想办法让你们脱身
I will try to free you
你凭什么认为我们会相信你
Why should we trust you?
因为你有两个孩子
Because you have two children
在马迭尔宾馆门口要饭
begging outside Modern Hotel
怎么找到小兰
How do I find Lan?
不是二四六一头一尾吗
It's Tuesdays, Thursdays, and Saturdays, right?
咱大白天盯啥呢
So why are we here now?
我过去看看
I'll go take a look
我也转转去
I'll go now
你走几趟我走几趟
If I don't match you
要不然高科长
I'll catch hell from
又该骂我了
Section Chief Gao
看过了
You've taken a look?
Yes
发现什么了吗
Did you find anything?
没有
No
真没发现什么
Really?
真没有
Really
看到了吗
Did you see that?
看到了
Yes
那你看到是谁画的了吗
Did you see who did it?
我是共产党
I am a Communist
如果我是共党
If I were a Communist
我刚才做了什么
you would never have seen
你根本就看不到
what I had just done
只有站在共党的角度
We can only catch Communists
才能抓共党
by thinking like them
而不是像你
and unlike you
整天想着
only watching during
盯紧二四六头尾就可以了
Tuesdays, Thursdays, Saturdays
高科长最在意细节了
Section Chief Gao cares about details
你要我把你的表现告诉他吗
Shall I tell him about this?
你知道你为什么这么多年一直升不上去吗
See why you've never been promoted?
今天你结帐啊
Coffee is on you
行
Fine
咋地啊
What's wrong?
打不着了
It won't start?
坐我车走吧
I'll give you a ride
不用
No, thanks
天冷
It's too cold
多打几次就着了
It will start after a few tries
来吧
Come on
来
Come
行啊
All right
你这刚修好的车比我的车还好使啊
Even after all that,
your car is still in good shape
今天中午一点半
Today's 1:30 show
要三张挨着的
Three seats together
靠前
Near the front
谢谢
Thank you
老金和张姐不在
Jin and Zhang Jie are not here
记住这两个杯子
remember these two cups
别搞错了
Don't get them mixed up
知道
All right
今天是十八号
Today is the 18th
终于不用等了
Finally the wait is over
现在能透露一点吗
Can you reveal a little more now?
无可奉告
No comment
那就只能聊吃的了
Then we can only talk about food
你看这俄木斯的红肠配红酒
Red sausage from Omsk with red wine,
红菜汤配黑面包
beet soup and black bread
现在能搞到这些已经很不错了
not easy to get these days
你们那边经常吃西餐吗
Do you often eat Western food?
西餐经常吃
Yes
不过还是中餐更合胃口
but I prefer Chinese food
那咖啡呢
Do you drink coffee?
咖啡倒是喝的惯
We drink coffee
头晕的厉害
I feel very dizzy
我先回去睡一会儿
I'm going to take a nap
我也有点晕
I feel dizzy, too
我送你啊
I'll walk you back
他怎么也倒了
Why is he down, too?
我看见他好像把杯子搞乱了
I think he mixed up the cups
一直就这样
He's always like that
见到酒什么都忘了
Alcohol distracts him from everything
楚良
Chuliang
你们就说今天晚上开始行动
Tell them the operation starts tonight
要一辆车
Get a car
沿着巴尔干大街
Drive along Balkan Street
到二十五号
to Number 25
那是罗马尼亚大使馆
the Romanian Embassy
到了门口以后
When you get to the door
你们要求停车
Stop the car
让其他人
Have the others
在外面等着
wait outside
你们俩进去
Two of you enter
门卫
The guard
会让你们出示请柬
will ask for an invitation
你们就说
Tell him
我是大使夫人的朋友
I am a friend of the ambassador's wife'
然后
Then
摘掉左手的手套
remove your left glove
他们会放行
They will let you in
今天晚上
Tonight is
是罗马尼亚大使夫人的生日
the Ambassador's wife's birthday party
会来很多人
There will be many guests
只要你们进去了
As long as you are in
不会有人问你们是谁
no one will ask who you are
进去之后
After you enter
穿过宴会厅
walk through the banquet hall
直接从后门出去
and exit directly via the back door
路边会停一辆黑色的轿车
A black sedan will be parked there
钥匙就在车上插着
The key will be in the ignition
车上有你们需要的一切
Everything you need will be in the car
这个计划我会想办法再告诉王郁
I will try to tell Yu this plan
这枪谁发现的
Who found this?
我亲手搜出来的
I found it on him myself
幸亏你提醒我要检查
It's a good thing you suggested we check
我说你们天天睡在一起都没发现
You all slept together night after night and didn't notice?
这跟小孟没有关系
Meng is not to blame
天天跟他睡一块的是我
It was me who shared a bed with him
那你怎么认为
So, what do you think?
我们已经暴露了
We've been made
应该立刻终止今天晚上的行动
We should abort tonight's operation
把他们抓起来
And detain them
还有没有其他解释
Is there any other explanation?
当然
Of course
还有另外一种可能
there is one other possibility
这只是一个特工的本能
That he was just being extra cautious
并不意味着我们已经暴露了
and that we haven't been made
他们还有多久醒来
How much longer till they wake up?
最多还有一个小时
One hour, at most
把枪送回去
Put back the gun
计划不变
The plan remains
今晚行动继续
We move tonight
是
Yes, sir
把枪的撞针搞了
Disable the firing pin
再放回去
before putting it back
谁也别说
Don't tell anyone
是
Yes, sir
你给我盯着
Keep watching them
看这把枪怎么开
Let's see what he needs a gun for
小孟
Meng
有火吗
do you have a light?
老周跟你说是我自己把杯子搞错的
Zhou told you I mixed up the cups?
是啊
Yes
你就是搞错了
You did mix them up
半个小时以后出发
We leave in half an hour
咱们这么多人
There are so many of us
目标是不是有点大
Will we stand out too much?
可是现在哈尔滨的特务太多
With so many spies in Harbin
大家在一起会比较安全
We'll be safer together
车上还得留个空位
Keep an empty seat in the car
回来的时候或许用得上
We may need it on our way back
那你
Then you
和我
and I
留下来待命
stay and wait for orders
好
Yes
不是让你待命吗
Didn't I say wait for orders
上级的安排
Orders from above
那空位子还留吗
Shall we keep the empty seat?
不留了
No need
去哪
Where to?
巴尔干大街
Balkan Avenue
巴尔干大街什么地方
Where on Balkan Avenue?
到了就知道了
You'll know when we get there
停车
Stop
就这啊
Here?
对
Yes
你们在这等着
Wait here
我跟楚良下去
Chuliang and I will get out
别熄火
Keep the engine running
等一下
Wait
那个大使是个反共分子
The Ambassador is anti-Communist
小心中了敌人圈套
It could be a trap
联络员在里面
The contact is inside
我们是按计划行动
We have our plan
我跟你们进去
I'll go with you
联络人要是发现来的人不对
If the contact sees it is not who he expects
会终止行动的
He will abort the operation
那也比中了敌人圈套强吧
That's better than falling into his trap
你说的对
You are right
要不计划取消吧
Why don't we abort?
我们回去
Let's call it off
先别走
Wait
我这也是担心你们的安全
I'm just worried for your safety
要不然这样
Why don't we do this
王郁姐
Sister Yu
你一个人进去
You go in alone
我们在外面等你
And we'll wait for you outside
好
All right then
我先进去
Here I go
你好夫人
Good evening, madam
您的请柬
Your invitation, please?
大使夫人是我的朋友
The ambassador's wife is my friend
出门的时候比较匆忙
I left the house in a rush
忘记带请柬了
and forgot the invitation
您贵姓
Your name, please?
我叫王郁
I am Wang Yu
是井田商会的
From the Idota Association
你好先生
Hello, sir
您的请柬
Your invitation, please
我跟刚刚进去那个女士是一起的
I'm with the lady who just entered
不好意思
Pardon me
您叫什么名字
What is your name, please?
我叫楚良
Chuliang
我把车停好
I'll park the car
我去看看
I'll have a look?
去吧
Go
是
Yes, sir
怎么开车的
Do you know how to drive?
下来
Get out
我要活的
I want them alive
分开走
Let's split up
走啊
Go
分开找
Split up
你们几个去那边
You go that way
记住啊
Remember
一定要抓活的
I need him alive
是
Yes
出来
Come out
把枪放下
Put down your gun
放下
Put it down
妈的
Damn
晚了一步
I was too late
死啦
He's dead?
服毒
He took poison
没来得及
Didn't get to him in time
那个女的呢
And the woman?
周股长果断开枪
Subsection Chief Zhou's sure shot
救了老金
saved Jin
因为他
because he...
我看见了
I saw
那把枪呢
And the gun?
开了没有
Was it shot?
开了
Yes
对方毫不犹豫先开的枪
The enemy fired without hesitation
要不是搞了撞针
If you hadn't disabled the firing pin
周股长就悬了
Zhou would be dead
弟兄们也都看见了
The men saw it, too
我认为周股长可以排除
I think Zhou is clean
你认为
Is that so?
人不行了
He's dead
没救过来
We couldn't save him
老金
Jin
科长让你先在这儿委屈几天
Gao said to stay here a few days
这次行动失败
This operation failed
一定是有人帮了他们
because they had help
我这算是
So then
被逮捕了吗
Are you arresting me?
你紧张什么
Why are you so nervous?
科长缴了我的械
You take my gun
还问我紧张什么
and ask me why I'm nervous?
我再问一遍
I will ask again
我这算是被逮捕了吗
Have I been arrested?
先回答问题
Answer me first
你认为是谁帮了他们
Who do you think helped them?
你是说大使馆的人
From the embassy?
我已经派人调查了使馆门口的白人小伙子
I had the guard investigated
拉脱维亚人
He's Latvian
有外交护照
with a diplomatic passport
我说的不是他
I don't mean him
那是谁
Then who?
谢子荣除了供出乌拉特行动外
Besides Operation Utrennya
还提供了一个重要情报
Xie provided other important intelligence
共产党的一名特工
A Communist special agent has
一直秘密潜伏在特务科
infiltrated our task force
谁
Who?
只知道是个男的
All we know is, it's a man
破获乌特拉行动只是一方面
Stopping Operation Utrennya was only a part
更重要的
The more important part is
是借这次行动
to use this operation
揪出内鬼
to find the mole
你不觉得金志德可疑吗
You don't think Jin is a suspect?
一个死了的人
What's so suspicious
有什么可疑的
about a dead man?
张宪臣用他的车越狱
Zhang used his car to break out
真是偶然吗
Is it really a coincidence?
是
Yes
这种事很多
These things often happen
这张电影海报很熟悉吧
You've seen this movie poster?
这是谁做的记号
Who made this mark?
我
I did
为什么
Why?
为了提醒金志德
To remind Jin
做事要认真细心
to pay attention to details
这也是高科长你的意思
Like you always taught us
金志德不是这样说的
That's not what Jin said
他怎么说
What did he say?
他不会胡说八道
He wouldn't lie
毕竟我们这么多年的同事
We've worked together so many years
他是怎么说的
What did he say?
为什么选二十号
Why did you choose the 20th ?
随手画的
I just made that mark at random
也是偶然吗
Is it by coincidence?
还是有什么特殊意义
Or is there a special significance?
科长我听不懂你的意思
I don't understand what you mean
听不懂
Don't you?
那你就在这坐到二十号吧
Then you will sit here until the 20th
起来
All up
开灯
Get up
起来
All up
都站起来
怎么找到小兰
How do we find Lan?
二四六  头尾两场
Tuesdays, Thursdays and Saturdays. First and last
选一个时间
Choose a time
画上勾
make a tick mark
保护措施是什么
What is the safety measure?
后四天的同一时间
Four days later from that time
她才会出现
is when she will show up
是后四天
Remember
记住
Four days later
这是从金志德的车里搜出来的
I found this in Jin's car
金志德
Jin?
坐我车走吧
I'll give you a ride
对你的调查到此为止
We're letting you go
怀疑是我的工作
It is my job to suspect people
也是我的职责
and my responsibility as well
别介意
Forgive me
周末我请你
This weekend I'll treat you to
马迭尔西餐
a meal at Modern Hotel
我不吃西餐
I don't like Western food
别那么小心眼儿
Don't be so petty
回去好好休息
Go home, get some rest
等等
Wait
这把枪可不能卡壳啊
This gun will not jam
我说嘛
I must say
科长
Section Chief
你救了我一命
You saved my life
老金
Jin
上级领导找你
The higher ups want to see you
有重要任务
There was an urgent mission
联系不上你
They couldn't find you
这紧急时刻
At this critical time
你们都在哪见面
where are you meeting?
老金
Jin
你怎么看
What do you think?
金志德的级别绝对在张宪臣之上
Jin definitely out-ranks Zhang
他能被自己人伤成这样
Can his own people hurt him so badly?
苦肉计而已
Gotta make it look real
我们常用
Comes with the territory
抓到了一个潜伏多年的共产党高级卧底
You've caught a high-level Communist spy
成果显著
who'd been in your ranks for years
这就是破获乌特拉行动的结果
The result of stopping Operation Utrennya
可以这样向上汇报
Can you report it this way?
科长英明
Brilliant, Section Chief
持枪
Ready
上膛
Load
瞄准
Aim
王子阳同志
Comrade Wang
我就送你到这里了
We part ways here
组织上已经安排好了
Everything has been arranged
出境会一切顺利
You'll be safe up to the border
我们后会有期
Take care
谢谢
Thank you
老韩  保重
Take care, Han
周乙大哥
Brother Zhou
现在任务已经完成了
Our mission is done
你可以告诉我
Please tell me
老张和楚良哥是怎么牺牲的
how Zhang and Chuliang died
不是说了很多回了吗
I've told you often
他们勇敢战斗
They fought bravely
把最后一颗子弹留给了自己
And saved the final bullet for themselves
他们没有被捕
They weren't arrested
没有被敌人折磨
or tortured?
没有
No
我都在现场
I was there
你都在现场
You were?
对
Yes
但是我没办法救他们
But I couldn't help
那天降落后
When we landed
楚良哥跟我说对不起
Chuliang apologized to me
其实是我对不起他
But I'm the one who should apologize
我都没有跟他好好告别
I didn't even say goodbye
没想到火车上远远看一眼
Our final meeting was
就是最后一面了
a distant glance on the train
你知道乌特拉是什么意思吗
Do you know what“Utrennya"means?
俄语里是黎明的意思
The Russian word for 'dawn'
老张最后跟我说
Zhang's last words to me were
天亮了就好了
Everything will be fine when the sun rises
我们
Will we
能看到天亮吗
get to see the sun rise?
那药片呢
Where is the pill?
在
Here
给我
Give it to me
我要你活着
I want you to live
看到天亮
To see the sun rise
把这个给金志德的家属
For Jin's family
顺便代我慰问一下
with my condolences
是
Yes, sir
科长
Section Chief
乌特拉行动上边已经结案了
Operation Utrennyas file is closed
内鬼还查吗
Do we still hunt the mole?
先放一阵子吧
Let it go for now
到时候让他自己跳出来
In time he will expose himself
妈妈
Your mother